<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://gsbaker.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://gsbaker.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-03-23T17:01:15+00:00</updated><id>https://gsbaker.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">George Baker</title><subtitle>Ruby on Rails developer based in the UK
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Reflecting on my University Experience</title><link href="https://gsbaker.github.io/university_reflection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflecting on my University Experience" /><published>2022-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://gsbaker.github.io/degree-reflection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gsbaker.github.io/university_reflection/"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, in a somewhat grand ceremony, I officially graduated from the University of Birmingham with a BSc in
Computer Science. Not an easy feat in the best of times, however, the past three years really weren’t the best of times. My <em>‘university
experience’</em> was split in half by a global pandemic which caused three national lockdowns. The consequences for university
students like me: societies, sports teams, face-to-face lectures, and supposedly some of our greatest years, all gone…</p>

<p>After struggling to find people who shared my interests at secondary school, I was relishing the opportunity to make lifelong
friends and develop myself at university. When I arrived, the Guild of Students provided over 300 societies to fuel
any niche (including a Tea Society), giving me the chance to pursue photography (a hobby I continue to enjoy to this day).</p>

<p>The infamous first week after moving in—<em>‘freshers week’</em>— was extremely hyped up by both the university and the Guild;
so much so that I purchased their £75 ticket for five <em>‘official’</em> events, of which I went to <em>one</em>, and later regretted.
I met hundreds (maybe thousands) of people in freshers week, and the vast majority of those people I never saw again.</p>

<p>Although I went to university in my home city, I decided to move into halls rather than live at home; this proved a wise
decision. Even though my flat didn’t gel (none of us kept in touch or stayed living together), the independence I gained
from living away from my parents and close to other students enabled me to gain key life skills and confidence.</p>

<p>As it turned out, all the close friendships I made were with fellow computer science students: perhaps this is because of our shared love
of technology, or just the fact that we worked on <em>many</em> assignments together.</p>

<p>I also found that even though I didn’t drink at all, nobody really cared. In fact, it enabled me to experience things
<em>as they were</em> without any filter; it turns out, a lot of the ridiculous alcohol culture and <em>‘initiation ceremonies’</em>
are either boring or seriously questionable.</p>

<p>After completing the first semester, I was really starting to settle in to university life. However, in March 2020—six
months after I had started—coronavirus sent the world into lockdown. Even when it became apparent that the UK would experience an outbreak, I naively thought that we’d all lock
ourselves at home for a couple of weeks and then the scare would be over. Evidently, I didn’t expect it
would last for two years when I packed just one month’s worth of clothes to take back home with me during my <em>‘escape’</em>.</p>

<p>It feels wrong to say, but I’ll admit that I was quite excited during the first lockdown: at last, I get to personally
experience a major world event. I remember that overnight, the international students—especially those from China—disappeared.
Clearly their families had told them how bad things really were. At first, I was relishing the <em>‘benefits’</em>: no exams! I can stay at home
and watch TV all I want! In fact, all I had to do to pass my first year was to spend an afternoon creating a simple
blog app.</p>

<p>The novelty quickly wore off… I can safely say that the second lockdown—during my second year—was
the worst period of my life. Here I was supposed to be having the best years of my life, stuck inside four walls that quickly
felt like a prison. I went through a major depression feeling like my life was being stolen away from me. On the flip side,
this period was also the catalyst for some major life changes: I ditched relationships that weren’t working and went
into therapy, perhaps the best decision of my life. This enabled me to use my third year—when things went back to
<em>‘normal’</em>—to explore myself and fully experience <em>‘university life’</em>.</p>

<p>During my third and final year, I threw myself into new things: tennis, photography, even karate. The misery of lockdown
prompted me to make sure that I <em>absolutely made the most</em> of the short rest of my time at university. I learnt not to be held
back by what other people might think and to prioritise my own needs. I started dating, and I now have
a wonderful girlfriend.</p>

<p>Academically, I was challenged, pushed to do my best work, and rewarded at the end with a 2:1 (after inadvertently picking
some of the most difficult third year modules). I learnt that AI is just probability, that nobody knows if P=NP, and
how to write <em>“Hello, World!”</em> in about ten different programming languages. I realised that computer science students
are <em>mostly</em> normal and also incredibly smart.</p>

<p>During my final year project, I even conducted my own research
into conformity on social media, and if you really want to, you can read my dissertation <del>here</del> (no longer available).
(though I’m not sure why you would).</p>

<div class="d-inline-flex w-100 flex-wrap">
<div class="w-50 p-2">
    <figure class="figure">
        <img src="/img/posts/dissertation.jpeg" alt="" class="img-fluid" />
        <figcaption class="figure-caption">Holding my dissertation</figcaption>
    </figure>
</div>
<div class="w-50 p-2">
    <figure class="figure">
        <img src="/img/posts/graduation.jpeg" alt="" class="img-fluid" />
        <figcaption class="figure-caption">Graduating in my cap and gown</figcaption>
    </figure>
</div>
</div>

<p>I started university as a shy and anxious teenage boy, and I’m leaving a confident young adult ready for the next
challenge. Having my university experience disrupted by the pandemic made it even more of a challenge; however, my
cohort and I got through it and showed incredible resilience in the hope that some day, life would be back to normal.
And when it did, I can safely say that I made the most of my final year, getting involved with sports clubs and
societies, and going to (just a few) parties! I’ll never forget the university, the people I met, and the journey I went
through. Whatever is next, I’m now ready for it!</p>]]></content><author><name>George Baker</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few weeks ago, in a somewhat grand ceremony, I officially graduated from the University of Birmingham with a BSc in Computer Science. Not an easy feat in the best of times, however, the past three years really weren’t the best of times. My ‘university experience’ was split in half by a global pandemic which caused three national lockdowns. The consequences for university students like me: societies, sports teams, face-to-face lectures, and supposedly some of our greatest years, all gone…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nonviolent Communication</title><link href="https://gsbaker.github.io/nvc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nonviolent Communication" /><published>2022-05-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://gsbaker.github.io/nvc</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gsbaker.github.io/nvc/"><![CDATA[<p>Nonviolent Communication (<abbr title="Nonviolent Communication" class="initialism">NVC</abbr>) is a method of
communication based on the assumption that we all share the same, basic human needs.</p>

<p>NVC assumes that physical and verbal violence—whether directed at ourselves or others—are learned behaviours taught
and supported by social structures.</p>

<h4 id="violent-communication">Violent Communication</h4>
<hr />

<p>NVC proposes that violent communication comes from <em>moralistic judgements</em>. It also challenges the notion that there
is <em>right</em> and <em>wrong</em>, or <em>good</em> people and <em>bad</em> people.</p>

<p>In this way of thinking, judgements about ourselves and others are discoraged:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“I’m a failure”</li>
  <li>“She talks too much”</li>
  <li>“I’m awful at talking to people”</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="punishment-and-reward">Punishment and Reward</h4>
<hr />

<p>NVC also challenges the way our social structures are predicated on <em>punishment</em> and <em>reward</em>, from the root
assumption that there exists <em>good</em> behaviour and <em>bad</em> behaviour.</p>

<p>Instead, NVC advocates <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Restorative_justice">restorative justice</a>.</p>

<h4 id="observations">Observations</h4>
<hr />

<p>NVC suggests that instead of moralistic judgements, we can use observations which are free from
thought/interpretation.</p>

<p>Observations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“He hasn’t done his homework in 10 days”</li>
  <li>“Each time we have a team meeting, Jen speaks for the majority of the time”</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="feelings">Feelings</h4>
<hr />

<p>One of the core components of NVC is <strong>feelings</strong>. NVC assumes that we all have the same basic human feelings
which are free from thought/interpretation. I.e., feelings just are.</p>

<p>Pseudo-feelings (not free from thought/interpretation):</p>

<ul>
  <li>“I feel like I didn’t get a fair deal”</li>
  <li>“I feel ignored”</li>
</ul>

<p>In our language, we often use sentences that start with <em>“I feel like…”</em>, however these are often voicing opinions
rather than feelings, e.g., <em>“I feel like I didn’t get a fair deal”</em>.</p>

<p>True feelings:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“I feel sad”</li>
  <li>“I feel embarrassed”</li>
  <li>“I’m scared”</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="needs">Needs</h4>
<hr />

<p>The other core component of NVC is <strong>needs</strong>. NVC assumes that we all have the same basic human needs:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Love</li>
  <li>Enjoyment</li>
  <li>Order</li>
  <li>Respect</li>
  <li>Safety</li>
</ul>

<p>When we relate to ourselves in terms of our feelings and needs, we can become more specific about what is not
making us happy.</p>

<p>E.g., <em>“I feel depressed”</em> can become <em>“I’m feeling lonely because I’m really needing some love and attention”</em>.</p>

<p>Getting in touch with our feelings and needs provides greater clarity to ourselves and others on how life could be
more wonderful.</p>

<h4 id="validating-feelings">Validating feelings</h4>
<hr />

<p><strong>Scenario</strong>: failing a test</p>

<p><strong>Invalidating response</strong>: <em>“you could have done this or that…”</em>. Feelings are ignored or discouraged.</p>

<p><strong>Validating response</strong>: <em>“wow, it is so hard that it didn’t turn out the way you wanted, I’m guessing you’re feeling upset right now”</em>. Feelings are acknowledged and respected.</p>

<h4 id="requests">Requests</h4>
<hr />

<p>NVC asserts that we cannot force other people to do what we want; conversely, nobody can force us to do what
we don’t want.</p>

<p>Instead NVC suggests using requests to other people based on our feelings and needs:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“I’m feeling tired right now and I’d like to rest. Would you be willing to reschedule to tomorrow?”</li>
  <li>“I feel annoyed when I hear you say ‘you won’t be able to do it’ because it doesn’t meet my need for respect. Would you be willing to give me a chance and some help in completing this task?”</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Nonviolent Communication is a method of communication based on the assumption that we all share the same, basic human needs.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Five Clothing Tips For Men</title><link href="https://gsbaker.github.io/fashion_tips/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five Clothing Tips For Men" /><published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://gsbaker.github.io/fashion-tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gsbaker.github.io/fashion_tips/"><![CDATA[<ol>
  <li><a href="#1-materials-construction-and-fit-are-much-more-important-than-the-brand">Materials, construction, and fit are much more important than the brand</a></li>
  <li><a href="#2-go-for-a-classic-style">Go for a classic style</a></li>
  <li><a href="#3-quality-over-quantity">Quality over quantity</a></li>
  <li><a href="#4-dress-for-your-environment">Dress for your environment</a></li>
  <li><a href="#5-never-buy-anything-without-research">Never buy anything without research</a></li>
</ol>

<h4 id="1-materials-construction-and-fit">1. Materials, construction, and fit</h4>
<hr />

<p>It is more important to consider the materials, construction, and fit of a piece of clothing than the brand. Just
because an item has a particular brand label—e.g., Armani Exchange—does not mean that it is worth its price.
<em>Expensive does not equal high quality.</em></p>

<p><strong>Materials</strong></p>

<p>A lot of cheaply made clothes and footwear are manufactured using synthetic fibres like polyester and acrylic. I would
recommend avoiding the aforementioned materials in most garments except outerwear—i.e., coats and
jackets—and sportswear.</p>

<p><img src="/img/posts/materials_info.jpeg" alt="Materials info" /></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption mb-3">Always check the materials information when shopping online. This ASOS jumper
is made from synthetics which are inferior to wool.</figcaption>

<p><strong>Construction</strong></p>

<p>Most clothes are machine stitched in a factory. Handmade clothes often have a superior construction—e.g., suits—but this
can have a big impact on price.</p>

<p><strong>Fit</strong></p>

<p>I recommend learning your key measurements—e.g., chest size. Ill-fitting clothing and footwear—no matter the quality,
price, or any other variable—is not worth it.</p>

<h4 id="2-go-for-a-classic-style">2. Go for a classic style</h4>
<hr />

<p>The big advantage of a classic style is that it will never go out of fashion: suits, blazers, shirts, and
a classic pear of jeans will always make a man look stylish.</p>

<p>I recommend avoiding so-called <em>“fashion forward”</em> items for two reasons:</p>

<ol>
  <li>they are often cheaply made and not to last;</li>
  <li>trends die out quickly.</li>
</ol>

<p>I also recommend investing in versatile pieces of clothing—e.g., neutral colours—because they can be worn often.</p>

<h4 id="3-quality-over-quantity">3. Quality over quantity</h4>
<hr />

<p>From experience, I think that it is better to buy one quality clothing item—which might be expensive—rather than
multiple cheaper ones.</p>

<p><em>Avoid impulse purchases</em>. I have a rule: if I want something, I add it to a list; if that item is
still on said list after two weeks, I can afford it, and it’s a good investment, I buy it. A good investment is
something that will often be worn; think about the <em>cost-per-wear</em>.</p>

<h4 id="4-dress-for-your-environment">4. Dress for your environment</h4>
<hr />

<p>Outfit choice should <em>heavily</em> depend on the climate you find yourself in. E.g., I live in the UK where it often
rains; my clothing should reflect that. It is also important to note that <em>dressing practically does not mean you have
to compromise on style</em>; in fact, function and style can often go hand in hand—look at the iconic Burberry trench coat.</p>

<p>I think it is also helpful to consider the original purpose of certain items of clothing and footwear. E.g., Converse were originally designed as basketball shoes—it is therefore no wonder they are completely impractical as everyday footwear.</p>

<h4 id="5-never-buy-anything-without-research">5. Never buy anything without research</h4>
<hr />

<p><em>Avoid buying items of clothing and footwear based solely on looks.</em> I highly recommend researching a particular item
of clothing before you decide whether to buy it.</p>

<p>Use Reddit to find out what other people think of a certain brand or product—just Google search “best men’s
<em>insert item</em> <strong>reddit</strong>”, or “is a <em>insert item</em> worth it <strong>reddit</strong>”, or “quality of <em>x brand</em> <strong>reddit</strong>”.
Sometimes, there can be lots of conflicting opinions on Reddit. Therefore, I recommend using it as a source of opinions
rather than truth. Having said that, I have found the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/malefashionadvice">r/malefashionadvice</a>
subreddit to be quite useful.</p>

<p>For researching footwear, the best place on the internet is without a doubt the YouTube channel
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/RoseAnvil">Rose Anvil</a>. He literally cuts shoes in half, explains what is in them, and
offers his expert opinion on if they are worth it.</p>

<p>Another YouTube channel that I highly recommend is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/Gentlemansgazette">The Gentleman’s Gazette</a>
which offers detailed content about classic men’s style. I particularly like their series of videos called
<em>“Is it worth it?”</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name>George Baker</name></author><category term="fashion" /><category term="fashion" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Materials, construction, and fit are much more important than the brand Go for a classic style Quality over quantity Dress for your environment Never buy anything without research]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Software engineering: 5 things they don’t teach you at university</title><link href="https://gsbaker.github.io/2021/09/10/fa-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Software engineering: 5 things they don’t teach you at university" /><published>2021-09-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://gsbaker.github.io/2021/09/10/fa-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gsbaker.github.io/2021/09/10/fa-post.html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://engineering.freeagent.com/2021/09/10/software-engineering-5-things-they-dont-teach-you-at-university/" target="_blank">https://engineering.freeagent.com/2021/09/10/software-engineering-5-things-they-dont-teach-you-at-university</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[https://engineering.freeagent.com/2021/09/10/software-engineering-5-things-they-dont-teach-you-at-university]]></summary></entry></feed>